<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honorable victorie obteined by graue Maurice his Excellencie, against the cittie of Rhyne-berg, the 20. of August. 1597 Translated out of the Dutch coppie, printed in S. Grauenhaghe, by Albert Hendrickson.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848388</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848388</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1606:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honorable victorie obteined by graue Maurice his Excellencie, against the cittie of Rhyne-berg, the 20. of August. 1597 Translated out of the Dutch coppie, printed in S. Grauenhaghe, by Albert Hendrickson.</title>
                  <author>Hendricks, Albert.</author>
                  <author>Maurice, Prince of Orange, 1567-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde for Thomas Stirrop: and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church yard at the signe the [sic] George[,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Graue Maurice his victorie against the enemies in Rhine-berg.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Rheinberg (Germany) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <p>The honorable Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie obteined by <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> his Excellencie, againſt the Cittie of <hi>Rhyne-berg,</hi> the 20. of Auguſt. 1597.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the Dutch Coppie,</hi> printed in <hi>S'Grauenhaghe,</hi> by <hi>Albert Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drickson.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at London by Edward Allde for <hi>Thomas Stirrop:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church yard at the ſigne the George.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:13478:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13478:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictorie against the Cittie of Rhyne-berg, <date>the 20.  of Auguſt 1597.</date>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, being come with his Armie into the Field, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing within the ſpace of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes, reduced the Towne of <hi>Berg</hi> vpon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Rhyne</hi> out of the hands of the Spaniſh Faction vnto the obedience of the vnited Prouinces of the Low Countries, hath ſignified the means how it was accompliſhed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſing the Agreement to the Lordes &amp; States of <hi>Holland,</hi> according to the Coppie following.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <pb facs="tcp:13478:3"/>
                        <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
                        <head>Maurice borne Prince of Orange, Countie of Naſſau, to the honorable, worshipfull, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and diſcreete our deere Frends, the States of Holland, or to their Deputies of the Counſell.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable, worſhipfull, prudent, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, and moſt aſſured good Frends,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>notwithſtanding the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance wee had certaine dayes by great raines and tempeſts, we tooke ſuch paines, that we made our approach euen to the walls of the Cittie, the which yeſterday morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wee ſummoned to yeelde after wee had made three vollies of Batterie. Whereupon the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; Captaines, at the firſt ſhewed themſelues deſirous of Parley with vs: but at laſt they requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red reſpit for three dayes. Hereupon wee continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our ſayd Batteries, and ſo effectually went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with our buſines, that in the afternoone we were out of the danger of their Ordinaunce, and got one of their Bulwarkes or Rauelins: &amp; were
<pb facs="tcp:13478:3"/>
                           <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
come ſo neere each to other at the ſaid Bulwarks, that we were readie to make a triall thereuppon. Which they within the Towne perceiuing, vpon our ſecond Summons, they deſired to haue Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley with vs, and ſent out certaine Captaines to fall to compoſition with vs. The which is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed according to the Contract inſuing. And this day about noone they are accordingly depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away. For the which wee yeeld moſt heartie praiſe and thankes to almightie God.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>Honorable, &amp;c.</salute> 
                           <dateline>In the Campe before Rhyne-berg.
<date>the 20. of Auguſt. 1597.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Vnderwritten.</hi> Your verie louing Frend. Subſcribed. <hi>Maurice Naſſau.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <pb facs="tcp:13478:4"/>
                        <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
                        <head>The Contract.</head>
                        <p>HIs Excellencie hath agreed and heereby a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeeth with the Gouernour, Captaines, Lieuetenants, Souldiers and Marriners remaining at this preſent within the Cittie of <hi>Rhyne-berg,</hi> That they ſhal freely and frankly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the ſaid Cittie, with their Armes, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and Baggage: and likewiſe all ſpirituall and temporall perſons, which will depart: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo al Officers that haue ſerued the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> Secondly, whatſoeuer appertaineth to the K. of <hi>Spaine</hi> within the ſaid Cittie, ſhall be left there, &amp; likewiſe the Ships of warre, and all mooueables that appertained to the Counteſſe of <hi>Neuwenar.</hi> The Citizens and Inhabitants ſhall be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their Priuiledges.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Done before Rhyneberg,
<date>the 19. of Auguſt. 1597.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13478:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->For which noble Victorie, the eternall God is to be praiſed and thanked. And God grant that his Excellencie may alwaies be bleſſed, and haue moſt proſperous ſucces in all his exployts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, that by his circumſpectnes and foreſight the Enemie may be quailed more and more, and that all ſuch as ſigh vnder the Spaniſh tyrannie, may be deliuered out of bondage.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printd by E. A. for Thomas Stirrop:</hi> and are to bee ſold at the ſigne of the George in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
